<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Fletcher Walmsley</title>
    <link href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io" />
    <updated>2020-07-20T15:53:13+12:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Fletcher Walmsley</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The HMNZS Otorohanga v1</title>
        <author>
            <name>Fletcher Walmsley</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/hmnzs-otorohanga/"/>
        <id>https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/hmnzs-otorohanga/</id>

        <updated>2020-07-20T15:52:19+12:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p> </p>
<p>The HMNZS Otorohanga is an on going project that I began during the 2019/2020 summer. The initial idea for the project began before this however, during Semester 2 of 2019. After completing an intro course into control systems, I had the desire to learn more about them. After watching videos on YouTube about autopilot systems for RC planes, I had the desire to create my own autopilot systems. My initial plan was to create a homemade RC plane auto pilot system. However, after a bit of research I decided that this might be biting off more than I could chew for a first attempt. The next idea was to create a land based rover. This time, I determined that this wasn't ambitious enough and would be relatively boring to watch. This is when I settled on creating an autonomous boat. This idea had the benefit of not falling out of the sky if something goes wrong, a lake would provide a large open area giving great GPS signal, and I determined that a boat was likely to be the easiest to built. </p>
<p>So, at the beginning of January, I placed a large order for electronic components from Alibaba and began planning.</p>
<p>The first parts that arrived were the GPS module, Bluetooth module and Magnetometer (compass). The photo below shows these components on a breadboard and connected to a Arduino Uno. With the left most is the GPS unit, the middle is the Bluetooth Module and the right most is the Magnetometer . </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/IMG_20200118_174526-2.jpg" alt="Figure 1: GPS and Magnetometer testing " width="444" height="333">
<figcaption >Figure 1: GPS and Magnetometer testing </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>With the above setup, an Android app was made using MIT's App Inventor  to send GPS coordinates to the Arduino over a Bluetooth connection. A screenshot of this App can be seen below</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/Seeker_App-2.jpg" alt="" width="212" height="448">
<figcaption >Screenshot of the GPS app</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>From here, the Ardunio would print out over the serial monitor to a connected Laptop what heading the user needed to walk in to reach the desired location, along with the current heading and the distance in metres from the location.</p>
<p>Next, Ardunio Nanos, the rudder servo, and some perf board arrived. So, with a basic design mapped out, I soldered some headers to the perf board and connected them together with pieces of scrap wire. The chosen design used two Ardunio Nanos, as it was feared that a single one won't enough the processing power due to the high amount of floating point arthritic that would be required due to both the GPS and magnetometer processing. </p>
<p>Once this board was made, I decide to create and test a PID controller for the rudder. For this test I mounted the magnetometer to the arm of the rudder servo and created a controller that would attempt to keep the magnetometer pointed towards a 0 degree heading. A video of this in action can be seen in below.</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j0m7tOLf_Ho" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" ></iframe></figure>
<p>Considering that the magnetometer and PID gains weren't optimally calibrated, along with the test being done in a metal shipping container, I was pretty happy with the result. Unfortunately, I burnt out a nano and my only magnetometer in the process, which stopped any further development in this area. Due to Covid-19, I have had delays in getting replacement components. As such, I am yet to continue developing the PID system.</p>
<p>Due to the magnetometer being a critical part in the automated boats control system, I decided to temporarily make the remotely controlled via Smartphone using Bluetooth. This process was relatively simple as I could use the same perf board that had already created, with the only major change being in software. As such, the app was updated to have a second screen that could be used to send throttle and steering commands adn the Ardunio code was modified to decode and respond to the apps requests. The throttle on the boat was controlled by using the PWM function of the Ardunio which varied the speed of a DC motor via a MOSFET. The steering control was done using the Ardunios inbuilt servo control library which aloud the for easy communication between the two. </p>
<p>A screenshot of the modified Android app can be seen below</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/Manual_Control.jpg" alt="" width="193" height="407">
<figcaption >Screenshot of the manual boat control portion of the App</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>With the code and electronics largely built, it was time to built the boat itself! The images below show the boat at various stages throughout the build. </p>
<div class="gallery"   >
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Above.jpg" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Above-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Top View of the the boat</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Duct_Tap.jpg" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Duct_Tap-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Underside of the boat while Duct Tape is being applied</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Overview.jpg" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Overview-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Boat with it's electronic components removed</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Rear.jpg" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Rear-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Read of the boat showing the prop</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Eletronic_Components_in_Tub.jpg" ><img src="https://fletcherpwalmsley.github.io/media/posts/6/gallery/Boat_Eletronic_Components_in_Tub-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="540"></a>
<figcaption>Image of the boat with all its electronic components installed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The boat itself was made out of foam boat, which was attached together with hotglue. The seals of which where covered with duct tape in case any gaps in the glue existed. </p>
<p>With all the required components installed, the HMNZS Otorohanga was now ready for testing. The videos below showcase both the App and the boat itself in action.</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Ga9dTswNfQ" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" ></iframe></figure>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-F4Rv8bRAQ" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" ></iframe></figure>
<p>This is the current state of the project. I have began working on communication between the boat and my Laptop, with shows the boats location in real time using Google Earth. However, I am still waiting on parts that will allow me to implement this development into the boat. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
